Hello and welcome back to
another video with ItsDrDan.
And today we're gonna be learning
how to further name different
compounds that you'll find in
introductory or general chemistry.
Specifically, we're gonna
learn how to name hydrates.
So what exactly are hydrates?
Well, typically you'll have a
bunch of different ionic compounds.
So whenever you have a cation,
which is your positive charge, and
an anion that are bonded together.
Very commonly, you'll see that
they will be, uh, essentially
surrounded by water molecules.
I have a little magnesium sulfate here and
I'm surrounding it by these little waters.
Um, so when it surrounds it,
it can change the properties
of the crystal that is forming.
So when you have magnesium sulfate
by itself, this is what we refer to
as anhydrous, meaning lacking water.
But when it's surrounded by
waters, that makes it hydrated.
So we're gonna take a look at all
the different naming for this.
So this one here, as I was shown, is
magnesium sulfate, um, and it also
has seven water molecules around it.
So we're gonna learn
how to name these guys.
Um, what they're all about has
been many of them that you'll
find in very common applications.
You can easily get like Epsom salt,
something easily buy at a grocery
store or a hardware, hardware store.
We're gonna take a look at all
the different naming rules.
Let's go.
So when naming different molecules
found in general chemistry, we follow a
systematic naming process, which is also
known as the IUPAC Convention for naming.
This is something we do
in general chemistry.
In organic biochemistry, we like
to follow a set of rules so that
everybody around the world can all
communicate about the same molecules.
So when we are looking at these, uh, first
thing you're gonna have to know is how
to name your ionic compounds, which has
been discussed previously in other videos.
Uh, here all we do is to take that name
and you're going to be labeling exactly
how many water molecules you have.
Using a prefix.
So we will write the word hydrate and
we will put a prefix in front of that.
So if I have like one
water, I'll put monohydrate.
I have two waters.
I'll put Dihydrate.
Three would be Trihydrate, tetra,
hydrate, pentahydrate, hexa,
hepta, Octa,  Nona and Deca.
So each one of those are going
to tell you exactly the number
that you have in your structure.
So if we go back to the one that I had
over here, which was MgSO4 for, well, we
would go through and we would name it just
like we would do for any ionic compound.
So we have our magnesium, then we would
name our sulfate portion of it, right?
So we have our oxy anion species
with our, uh, compound, and
now we're gonna use a prefix.
So being that we have a, we
have seven waters that are here.
So we're gonna be using the HEPTA prefix.
We got seven from right here.
So all we're going to say is hepta
hydrate for the name, and that's
just one word for the hydrate.
Um, there's a little space between them.
Let's do a bunch of examples and
see if we can fully understand this.
Uh, so if you have to, let's
say, solve for the molar mass
of this compound, you're going
to add to waters in this case.
We're adding water, not multiplying.
It is not a multiply symbol, just
letting you know how many waters
are surrounding this molecule.
So if we are to do this
one, how would we name it?
We have calcium is our metal,
and then we have chloride.
And then how many we see,
how many waters do we have?
Well, we're gonna look and we notice
that, okay, well we have two waters, so
we're gonna use the dye, uh, prefix here.
So with that being said,
we'll have calcium chloride.
Dihydrate would be the name.
So Dihydrate, and that would be
the name of our molecule here.
Okay.
That we have those two waters
surrounding calcium chloride.
Let's take a look at another example.
So I have CuSO4 with five
waters attached to it.
So once again, we're gonna
go through our naming here.
So we have copper as our molecule.
And being that this is a transition metal,
we have to include what the charge is.
It's copper two.
The way that I got that was being
that sulfite, say, sorry, sulfate
as a two minus charge making copper.
Have a two plus we'll have copper sulfate.
And being that we have five waters,
we're gonna use our prefixes here.
So we go down to the bottom and
we can see that Penta is five.
So we're gonna have copper
sulfate, and the hydrate is going
to be my name for this molecule.
Okay, so sodium, or sorry, copper sulfate.
And the hydrate.
Now with this particular molecule, um,
with many of the different hydrates,
something about them is that we
are able to actually separate the
water from it by either manipulating
them or by natural processes.
So one thing that can happen is this,
uh, process known as efflorescence, which
is when a hydrate loses its water due
to it being exposed to certain things
in the atmosphere or if you heat it up.
So one thing here is you
see on the left-hand side is
this very rich blue color.
So this is the copper sulfate
with five waters attached to it.
Now the one on the right hand
side is when all the waters are
removed or they're separated.
So we can see that these guys kind of
like go away and they evaporate away.
Um, and as a result, it loses
its color because the structure
of the molecules is changing.
Um, here I have a, a short video
to illustrate this process.
So we have copper sulfate and it's
in a liquid right now, so it's
dissolved and we're heating it up here.
And one thing that you're going
to start seeing is that, uh,
it's starting to evaporate.
And if you look very, very closely,
you can see that the edges are
actually starting to turn a white
color, which has shown you that it's
losing all of its water, and then the
blue color is completely going away.
As that is lost.
Okay.
So it's changing from those, uh,
from those two structures there.
Um, because the water is being removed.
So this is efflorescence.
It's something that happens
a lot with like concrete.
If you have like staining on the concrete
structures, it happens around dams.
You see that there might be a staining
from different salts in the concrete
that eventually come out as well.
A very common process around them
when sodium acetate trihydrate.
Let's see if we could do this one.
So being that we have sodium, so
that is NA now that is NA plus.
So now the next part is you have
to look up what your acetate, uh,
ion is for this next structure.
So if once, if you look that up,
you'll quickly see that it's CHC
two, H 3 0 2 minus is your structure.
Um, so these will swap, drop, they
will balance with one another,
exchanging their electrons so
we can get rid of those charges.
Now, being that we have three
waters that we see here, right?
There's that tri symbol, so we'll
use the little dot, put the, let
put the number three, and then
put the water molecule after.
So this is letting you know that
you have three waters attached to
sodium acetate in this example.
Okay?
This is the end of this video for now.
I hope that this helped you understand
the basic idea of hydrates going
through numerous examples, going
through from having the name
and then also from the formula.
This is something that is very common
application and a lot of different,
um, a lot of household ingredients
and chemicals that you'll see.
If you look at a lot of labels, you'll
see that things are hydrates, especially
with a lot of beauty products and also a
lot of things with medicinal applications.
Seeing that hydrates are typically
a more stable way to ship and
send out different things that you
might ingest or that you might use
Meditionally or just as a supplement.
Uh, so this is how we do hydrate naming.
Thank you so much for listening.
I hope that this video helped.
You'll later please set that like
and subscribe button if you have it.
Bye now.